A Finding Aid to the John Graham Papers, 1799-1988, bulk 1890-1961, in the Archives of American Art AAA.grahjohn
Archives of American Art
John Graham papers
bulk 1890-1961
1799-1988
AAA.grahjohn
Archives of American Art
11.4 Linear feet
The papers of painter, collector, and writer John Graham measure 11.4 linear feet and date from 1799 to 1988, with the bulk of materials dating from 1890 to 1961. Papers document the life of John Graham, born Ivan Dombrowsky, through personal documents related to military service and family history, passports, artifacts, correspondence, appointment books, financial records, inventories, wills, extensive writings and notes, books, clippings, exhibition catalogs, photographs of Graham and his family and friends, and artwork created and collected by Graham.
John Graham
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of John Graham were given to the Archives of American Art in five separate accessions between 1985 and 1988. The bulk of papers were donated by Graham's son, John David Graham, in 1985, with later additions from Patricia Graham, the widow of John David Graham, in 1986, 1987, and 1988, via the Andre Emmerich Gallery Inc. The Department of Prints and Drawings of the Museum of Modern Art donated additional materials in 1986.
Separated Materials note
Notebooks and drawings by John Graham dated circa 1935-1957 are in the collections of the Museum of Modern Art. These notebooks and drawings were microfilmed by the Museum of Modern Art along with materials donated by the museum in 1986. A microfilm copy of the notebooks and drawings in MoMA's collection was loaned with publication restrictions to the Archives of American Art and can be viewed on reel 5049.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The papers of John Graham in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2008. The bulk of Graham's papers have been scanned and total 13475 images.
Materials that generally have not been scanned include photographs of works of art (except installation views), card files of handwritten essays for which there are typed versions, bank statements, and stocks and tax files.
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection has been digitized and is available online via the Archives of American Art website.
Biographical/Historical note
The Russian émigré painter and writer John Graham, born Ivan Dombrowsky, was born in Kiev in 1886, 1887, or 1888. All three conflicting dates are found on various legal papers, licences, and passports. His parents were of minor nobility but with little means. He attended law school and served in the Circassian Regiment of the Russian army, earned the Saint George's Cross during World War I, and was imprisoned as a counterrevolutionary by the Bolsheviks after the assassination of Czar Nicholas II and his family in 1918. He fled for a time to his mother's native Poland, and finally in 1920, he emigrated with his second wife Vera and their son Nicholas to the United States. He began calling himself John in the US, and had his name officially changed to John Graham upon becoming a United States citizen in 1927. The name Graham may have been a transliteration of his father's name, Gratian. Graham is often described as a quixotic figure who cultivated a larger-than-life persona in the artistic circles of New York in the first half of the twentieth century through his authoritative philosophical and aesthetic arguments on the one hand, and his often fabulous tales of his early life on the other, including a story he wrote of his origins in which he was dropped as an infant onto a rock in the Caspian Sea by an enormous eagle.
In New York, Graham studied at the Art Students League, taking classes with John Sloan, William von Schlegell, and Allen Tucker. Among his fellow students were Dorothy Dehner and David Smith, Adolph Gottlieb, Alexander Calder, and Elinor Gibson, who married Graham in 1924. The couple lived briefly in Elinor's native Baltimore, Maryland, where he met Etta and Claribel Cone, collectors of modern European paintings. It may have been the Cone sisters who introduced Graham to their circle of avant-garde artists and art collectors in Paris in the late 1920s. Whatever its origin, Graham's early style has been compared to Cezanne, Braque, Derain, and Chirico, and his frequent trips to Europe made him a conduit for current art ideas and trends for the American artists who knew him.
Graham exhibited his paintings steadily in the late 1920s and early 1930s, including shows at the Society of Independent Arists (New York) in 1925, the Modernist Galleries (Baltimore) in 1926, Galerie Zaborowski (Paris) in 1928 and 1929, at Dudensing Galleries (New York) and Phillips Memorial Gallery (Washington) in 1929, the First Biennial at the Whitney Museum in 1932, and at 8th Street Gallery (New York) in 1933. During this period Graham and his wife Elinor lived in Paris, New York City, New Jersey, and upstate New York. He spent a year teaching at Wells College in Aurora, New York, where he also executed a series of wall panels in 1932. Graham's friendships with other artists during this period included Arshile Gorky, Stuart Davis, and Willem de Kooning. De Kooning is said to have called Davis, Gorky, and Graham the "three smartest guys on the scene."
Graham's European travels also enabled him to earn a living by buying primitive sculpture and antiques for collectors and dealers. In the 1930s he bought African Art for Vanity Fair editor and art collector Frank Crowninshield, and in 1936, Graham arranged an exhibition of Crowninshield's collection at Jacques Seligmann gallery. Graham and Elinor Gibson divorced in 1934 and he married Constance Wellman in Paris in 1936. They lived in Brooklyn Heights near Adolph Gottlieb, David Smith, and Dorothy Dehner, and worked for Hilla Rebay in her formation of the Museum of Non-Objective Painting, which became the Guggenheim Museum. Suffering financial hardship in the late years of the Depression, Constance and Graham lived in Mexico for several stretches of time, and Graham published several articles on Mexico and Mexican Art, and an essay entitled "Primitive Art and Picasso" in Magazine of Art.
Graham was a prolific writer, but only a few of his written works found their way into print. Aside from his essays, published works include a small book of poetry, Have It!, published in 1923, and a book which presented Graham's personal theories of art entitled System and Dialectics of Art, published in 1937 by Delphic Studios, an eclectic New York gallery and small press run by Alma Reed. The book was influential for a younger generation of American artists; Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner in particular both expressed appreciation for Graham's ideas. For decades, Graham worked on several other major written works which were not published, including a highly stylized, symbolist work about his childhood and an encyclopedic collection of short, didactic essays on a wide range Grahamiam themes, a work which Graham usually referred to as Orifizio Mundi.
In 1942, Graham organized the exhibition "French and American Painters" at McMillen Gallery (New York) which showed Modigliani, Picasso, Braque, Rouault, and Matisse, alongside the Americans Jackson Pollock, Willem de Kooning, Lee Krasner, Stuart Davis, David Burliuk, and Walt Kuhn, among others. The show was well-received critically and, as it was Jackson Pollock's first public exhibition and Willem de Kooning's second, and the occasion of Pollock and Lee Krasner's meeting, could be considered a watershed event in contemporary American art.
Graham's own style made a pronounced shift away from abstraction in the 1940s. He began referencing renaissance art in his paintings, incorporating occult symbols, and signing them "Ioannus Magus," or "Ioannus San Germanus." His marriage to Constance ended acrimoniously around this time. He met Marianne Strate, a bookbinder, through her daughter Ileana Sonnabend and son-in-law Leo Castelli. They lived in Southampton, New York, where Graham was close to the Castellis, Paul Brach, Miriam Schapiro, and where he renewed his friendship with Willem de Kooning, who had a studio in Castelli's East Hampton home in the early 1950s. Marianne died in 1955.
Graham exhibited at the Stable Gallery in 1954, and at the newly-opened, uptown Whitney Museum of American Art in 1955. Jack Mayer became Graham's dealer in the late 1950s, held exhibitions at his Madison Avenue gallery, Gallery Mayer, in 1960, and arranged for an exhibition at the Tennessee Fine Arts Center in 1961, shortly before Graham's death. Graham left the United States for the last time in 1959, lived in Paris for two years, and died in June 1961 in a hospital in London. Gallery Mayer held a memorial exhibition at the end of 1961. Retrospective exhibitions of Graham's work have been held at the Art Institute of Chicago (1963), the Museum of Modern Art (1968), the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston (1969), and the Phillips Collection (1987).
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter, collector, and writer John Graham measure 11.4 linear feet and date from 1799 to 1988, with the bulk of materials dating from 1890 to 1961. Papers document the life of John Graham, born Ivan Dombrowsky, through personal documents related to military service and family history, passports, artifacts, correspondence, appointment books, financial records, inventories, wills, extensive writings and notes, books, clippings, exhibition catalogs, photographs of Graham and his family and friends, and artwork created and collected by Graham.
Biographical Materials and Artifacts include passports and other official documents, as well as records related to Graham's family, military service, and medical history. Among the artifacts are paint pots and a palette. Correspondence is with art and antique dealers and collectors, and includes significant correspondence and related documents of Jack Mayer, Graham's agent from the late 1950s. Several artists and famous friends are represented in Graham's correspondence including David Burliuk, Stuart Davis, Ultra Violet, Francoise Gilot, R.B. Kitaj, Marc Tobey, and Ron Gorchov.
Personal Business Records contain appointment books spanning 1931 to 1961 which record appointments but were also used as notebooks and sketchbooks. Other Business Records include inventories of Graham's books and antiques made by Graham, records of antique-related transactions, wills of Graham and his last wife, Marianne Strate, and extensive personal financial records from the last few years of his life.
Graham's writings are found scattered throughout the collection, as is his artwork. The Writings series is dominated by Graham's lengthy book projects, found in multiple drafts. The author's annotated published works are also found, as well as typescripts of several published essays by and about Graham. Lists, notes, and writings on a wide range of subjects are found on loose pages and in notebooks dated from 1931 to 1961. Among the Printed Materials are many annotated books from Graham's library, some of which contain drawings, and clippings and exhibition catalogs related to Graham's career going back to the 1920s. Reference files of printed ephemera and clippings collected by Graham are found on a variety of subjects, some of which contain pictorial subjects used in Graham's paintings.
Photographs depict Graham from childhood through his last years in cabinet card portraits, passport photographs, and snapshots. Photographs are also found of his parents, his five wives and four children, and a number of famous friends including Pablo Picasso, Françoise Gilot, their children, and Arshile Gorky. Artwork includes Graham's sketchbooks of 1934, 1960, and 1961, loose sketches, and a collection of file folders with many symbols and illustrations. Also found among the artwork are antique and contemporary prints and drawings collected by Graham.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Materials and Artifacts, 1799, 1822, 1891-1961 (Boxes 1, 11-12, 17; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1932-1988 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, circa 1931-1962 (Boxes 1-3; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1839, circa 1923-1986 (Boxes 3-5, OV 13; 2.9 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Materials, circa 1885-1961 (Boxes 6-9, OV 14; 3.7 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1860-1985 (Box 9-10, 17, OV 15; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1852-1961 (Box 10, OV 16; 1 linear foot)
Burliuk, David, 1882-1967; Davis, Stuart, 1892-1964; Gilot, Francoise, 1921-; Gorchov, Ron; Gorky, Arshile, 1904-1948 -- Photographs; Kitaj, R. B.; Mayer, Jack; Picasso, Pablo, 1881-1973 -- Photographs; Tobey, Mark; Ultra Violet; Antiques; Art--Collectors and collecting; Artists as authors--New York (State)--New York; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, Modern--20th century--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Works of art; World War, 1914-1918
- Biographical Materials and Artifacts, 1799; 1822; 1891-1961; Series 1; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 1, 11-12, 17
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of documents related to John Graham's military service, legal matters, medical history, family members, as well as three-dimensional artifacts belonging to Graham.
  Many of the documents in this series are in Polish or Russian, and typescript translations are often available. Translations appear to have been annotated and perhaps written by Graham. These documents include a baptism certificate, a certificate of nobility, documents related to Graham's military service and nationality, and certificates of identity. Graham's marriages and divorces are documented through legal records, invitations, correspondence in Russian with a third party related to his divorce from Vera Alexandrovna, and an identity paper of Constance Wellman with a photograph issued in France.
  Two scrapbooks related to Archer Gibson, Graham's father-in-law by his third marriage to Elinor Gibson and a well-known organist, are found. The first contains primarily newspaper clippings related to Gibson's musical career. The second contains letters and telegrams from well-known politicians, industrialists, and other celebrities for whom Gibson gave concerts. For photographs of Archer Gibson, see the Photographs series.
  Medical documents include a report of Graham's death issued by the State Department and x-rays taken in 1961, shortly before his death.
  Among the artifacts are four vellum-bound books, two of which bear dates from the late 18th and early 19th century. Some of the Artwork among Graham's papers appears to have been made on paper taken from these books. Also found is a fragment of music on vellum, which is likely the Nicene Creed. Relating to David Graham is a naval patch representing the rank of a Recruit Chief Petty Officer.
  Additional biographical documents, including Graham's will and lists of assets, are found in Personal Business Records.
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Driver's Licenses and other ID's, 1942-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Drawing of Lubicz Family Crest, circa 1910-1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of Introduction, 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Marriage to and Divorce from Vera Alexandrovna, 1918-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Marriage to and Divorce from Elinor Gibson Graham, undated; 1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Marriage to and Divorce from Constance Wellman, 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    includes photograph
  - Natural Father's Consent to Adoption, Nicholas Dabrowsky, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Passports and Other Travel Documents, circa 1925-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal Documents, Poland and Russia, 1891-1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbooks of Archer Gibson, circa 1895-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    see Box 11, sol
  - Items Removed from Archer Gibson Scrapbooks, circa 1895-1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Not scanned
  - State Department Report of Death, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - X-Rays, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Partially scanned
  - Artifacts (Box 1)
    - Hair, circa 1936; undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
      (Envelopes only scanned)
    - Paint Pots, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
      See Box 12, sol
    - Palette, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Vellum-Bound Books, 1948; undated; 1799; 1822; 4 volumes (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Mostly blank pages; partially scanned; see Box 12, sol
    - Baby Shoe, Russian Money, and Feathers, 1898; undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - David Graham's Naval Patch, circa 1940s (Box 17, Folder 1)
      Recruit Chief Petty Officer
    - Vellum Fragment, Music, circa 1700s (Box 17, Folder 2)
      Probably the Nicene Creed
  - Oversized Scrapbooks of Archer Gibson (See Box 1, folder 11) (Box 11 (sol))
  - Paint Pots, Palette, and Vellum-Bound Books (See Box 1, folders 16-18) (Box 12 (sol))
- Correspondence, circa 1932-1988; Series 2; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains personal and business correspondence, and consists primarily of letters received by Graham from family members, artists, patrons, art and antique dealers, health practitioners, and other associates. Third-party correspondence and letters written by Graham are found among his family's letters and the letters of Jack Mayer. In general, arrangement is alphabetical by correspondent. Incidental letters and letters from unidentified correspondents are filed at the end of the series in miscellaneous files for business, medical, and personal correspondence.
  Significant correspondents include David Burliuk, Stuart Davis, Ultra Violet, Francoise Gilot, R.B. Kitaj, and Marc Tobey. Among Elinor Gibson Graham's letters is third-party correspondence with attorney Paul Arnold regarding Graham's estate, a letter signed Dorothy which may have been written by Dorothy Dehner, and letters from Eila Kokkinen, Constance Wellman, and Charles Shaw. Jack Mayer's correspondence also contains lists of paintings and third-party correspondence with interested patrons. A photograph of Jan Tice is found with a letter from Ron Gorchov, and an illustrated letter is among Tice's letters to Graham.
  Miscellaneous business correspondence includes letters regarding Graham's antique business, financial affairs, real estate, publishing, responses to letters Graham wrote to politicians, and scattered receipts for personal items. Also found is a letter from a New York Public Library linguist and a letter form a Harvard architect with advice to Graham about employment. Miscellaneous medical correspondence includes letters from a variety of doctors and healers, including Julie Owen, the British practitioner of a bee sting cure. Miscellaneous personal correspondence is separated by the language in which letters are written; undated letters which may be from Graham's early years are found among the letters in Polish and Russian. Names found in miscellaneous personal correspondence are listed in the folder list.
  Additional scattered correspondence is found in Biographical Materials and Personal Business Records.
  - American Society for Psychical Research, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ash, Maxwell, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bayley, John B., circa 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Beck, Rosemarie, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bennett, J.G. (Institute for the Comparative Study of History, Philosophy, and the Sciences), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Browislawa, Francryniska, circa 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Buford, Richard, circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Burliuk, David, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bultman, Fritz, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - The Collector's Corner, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Crowninshield, Frank, circa 1936-1947 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Davies and Son, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Davis, Stuart, circa 1932 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Ehrenpreis, Bernard, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Gabrielson, Galin and Karen, 1947-1959 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gilot, Françoise, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Graham, Elinor Gibson (Box 1)
    - General, circa 1936-1977; 2 Folders (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - Letters from John Graham, circa 1935-1960; 2 Folders (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Graham, John David (son), 1961; circa 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Granick, Max, circa 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Grinberg, Leon, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Gorchov, Ron, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - J.J. Klejman, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Kitaj, R.B., circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Korabiewska, Felicja, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Leyden, Frank, circa 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Leyden, Linda, 1959-1961; 5 Folders (Box 1, Folder 48-52)
  - Malval, Henry de, circa 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Mayer, Jack (Gallery Mayer), 1959-1961; undated (Box 1, Folder 54-56)
  - Meyer, Michel, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Museum of Primitive Art (Robert Goldwater), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Parke-Bernet Galleries, Inc., 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Press, Lorence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Ratton, Charles, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Rieger, Charles, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Saling, Victoria, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Saxer, Walter, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Skutch, Robert Frank, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Spink and Son, Ltd., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Staempfli Gallery (Phillip Bruno and Wilfrid Zogbaum), 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Steinberg, Harris, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Strate, M.N., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Tice, Jan, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Thorne, Nicholas (son), circa 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Tobey, Marc, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Ultra Violet (Isabelle Collin du Fresne), circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Verdier, Andie, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Von Wiegand, Charmion, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Weinberg, Usana, circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Miscellaneous Business Correspondence, circa 1938-1961 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Miscellaneous Medical Correspondence, 1949-1961 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Miscellaneous Personal Correspondence in English, French, and Spanish, circa 1934-1961; 2 Folders (Box 1, Folder 80-81)
    Includes 2 letters from Graham, one a fragment; and letters from Joan Graftmueller, Edwin Walker, Paule Peron, Charles Schante, Harry Dickman, an Abrams (possibly Ruth Abrams), Marguerite Mergin, Mrs. M. Graham, Ilse Pichler, Islmail Loutfi, Coucha, Katie (a nurse in London), Wilfred (possibly Zogbaum), Betsy (possibly Elizabeth Sparhawk Jones), Jean Marie, Blanche (possibly Blanche Battaglia) and several unsigned letters.
  - Miscellaneous Personal Correspondence in Polish and Russian, 1940-1961; undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Miscellaneous Envelopes, circa 1946-1961 (Box 1, Folder 83)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1931-1962; Series 3; 1.4 Linear feet Box 1-3
  This series contains address books, appointment books, contracts, receipts, banking documents, property inventories, stock records, tax records, notes, notebooks, wills and other legal documents, and scattered correspondence related to Graham's finances. Apart from the appointment books and inventories which are earlier, records in this series are dated from the late 1950s to Graham's death.